GOVINDA Das: Oh, my God!
GOVINDA Das: Jackson.
GOVINDA Das: Oh, Mushnupada, yeah.
GOVINDA Das: Krishna brush.
GOVINDA Das: So I'm muting on a minute.
GOVINDA Das: Namaste, sir.
GOVINDA Das: Negotiations from Nemadi will start with each other.
GOVINDA Das: Wonderful.
GOVINDA Das: What are you talking about?
GOVINDA Das: Hari Grishma Hari Grishma Grishma.
GOVINDA Das: How do you know? How do you know?
GOVINDA Das: Welcome all.
GOVINDA Das: Yesterday, We discussed about the… overview of Planet Mon…
GOVINDA Das: Briefly, Nakshatra, Lagna, and then we discussed about the concept of
GOVINDA Das: Sade sati, dasha, little bit, and then we discussed the gochar.
GOVINDA Das: In fact, Gochar is what is responsible.
GOVINDA Das: for creating Sadesh Sati.
GOVINDA Das: And then Dr. Karan discussed about the
GOVINDA Das: the principle of Vastu, based on different foundational ideas.
GOVINDA Das: Today, we will touch base upon the influence of Grahas.
GOVINDA Das: where people translate that as a planet. There is a huge difference between graha and planet.
GOVINDA Das: We'll see that.
GOVINDA Das: Agraha is not identical to the astronomical planet.
GOVINDA Das: A planet is a place.
GOVINDA Das: Graha is beyond a place.
GOVINDA Das: When you study the words vidya and education.
GOVINDA Das: You can see the distinction between the two.
GOVINDA Das: Vidya is a living force.
GOVINDA Das: That is prana.
GOVINDA Das: Education is a neutral gender.
GOVINDA Das: Vidya is not.
GOVINDA Das: Right? Lakshmi. Vidya.
GOVINDA Das: Shakti.
GOVINDA Das: Street.
GOVINDA Das: Putra, Putri.
GOVINDA Das: So, these words… They do not just represent the physical aspect.
GOVINDA Das: So, the planet… Is very stool, it's very gross.
GOVINDA Das: But Garha is not.
GOVINDA Das: The planet is the physical substrates, tula, so therefore.
GOVINDA Das: when they, astronomers… When they're studying astrophysics.
GOVINDA Das: They do not focus on how they impact.
GOVINDA Das: They focus on what they are.
GOVINDA Das: From purely from the science perspective.
GOVINDA Das: The Graha does not denote the modern science, Graha denotes.
GOVINDA Das: Vedic Vijayan.
GOVINDA Das: Now, Vedic Vijayan is not synonymous to modern science because Vedic Vijayan.
GOVINDA Das: Does not always agree to Pratiksha Pramad.
GOVINDA Das: And without Pratiksha Pramana, modern science cannot establish it as a science. There has to be direct evidence.
GOVINDA Das: So sometimes we try to make everything as a science which is undermining.
GOVINDA Das: The power of Vedic knowledge.
GOVINDA Das: Right, therefore… The Graha is the subtle principle it represents. It is Sukshma.
GOVINDA Das: Right? When you study, we will bring the Bhagavatam concept also.
GOVINDA Das: The route Graha… Means to say is to grasp, to influence.
GOVINDA Das: Right, what is it? It influences our consciousness.
GOVINDA Das: And enters into that space.
GOVINDA Das: Right?
GOVINDA Das: Therefore… Astronomy studies the object.
GOVINDA Das: Jyotish studies its meaning. Jyotish means to
GOVINDA Das: Put a light. Prakash. Prakash Smai.
GOVINDA Das: Right, there is a huge distinction between the two.
GOVINDA Das: So, therefore, The entire… cosmos Your home is called as Griha.
GOVINDA Das: Graham Pravesh.
GOVINDA Das: Right. We also have the 7 days.
GOVINDA Das: Raviwar, Somuwar, Mangalwar, Buddhuwar, Guruwar, Shukurwar, Shaniwar.
GOVINDA Das: What do they do?
GOVINDA Das: These planets, these grahas, They influence according to what power, what influence they're representing.
GOVINDA Das: In the Bharatiya Sanskriti, Sunday is not a holiday.
GOVINDA Das: Right.
GOVINDA Das: It is so Abrahamic in regards to Sunday is the day when
GOVINDA Das: God, after creating the creation, rested.
GOVINDA Das: But from the grass perspective, Sunday is the day when you are more active.
GOVINDA Das: Surya.
GOVINDA Das: Or the day of confidence, the day of action, the day of feeling kingship.
GOVINDA Das: Because Surya represents that.
GOVINDA Das: All right.
GOVINDA Das: If you want to actually take off.
GOVINDA Das: The best day is Monday and Friday.
GOVINDA Das: Both Sunday and Saturday are the day when people are supposed to work.
GOVINDA Das: Friday has to be very soft, because it is pleasure-driven, comfort-driven, resources-driven. Monday is the feeling-driven.
GOVINDA Das: The Friday gives you the juice.
GOVINDA Das: And Monday gives you the feeling.
GOVINDA Das: And therefore… When people have to go to work on Monday, they always have much duller consciousness.
GOVINDA Das: Kiki, these are feminine planets. These are feminal graphs.
GOVINDA Das: So, therefore, when you study objectively as an object.
GOVINDA Das: And when you study Jyotish here, trying to look for meaning, they have such a contradiction from each other.
GOVINDA Das: We are not saying this is right, that is wrong, this is correct, that is false. The perspective, the purpose, the process.
GOVINDA Das: Everything differs from each other.
GOVINDA Das: This requires… Purely modern technology to… Dissect.
GOVINDA Das: Right, the, the scientific person, the modern scientific person.
GOVINDA Das: He's not interested in how the Graha's impact, because he doesn't see them as Graha, he sees them as a planet.
GOVINDA Das: or objective.
GOVINDA Das: We don't say it as an object.
GOVINDA Das: We see it as an influence, therefore, to capture, to grasp, to influence.
GOVINDA Das: to consume.
GOVINDA Das: Right?
GOVINDA Das: So this is one of the greatest distinction.
GOVINDA Das: Therefore, trying to miss, trying to fix everything, oh, this modern size is connected to, you know, this scripture or that scripture.
GOVINDA Das: That is a overkill.
GOVINDA Das: Plus, it is Tamoguna.
GOVINDA Das: You know, some other trying to…
GOVINDA Das: Connect everything to everything and call it, oh, this was already there in the Vedas.
GOVINDA Das: That is not a fair play, because
GOVINDA Das: It is not we are convincing them, we are ridiculing ourselves.
GOVINDA Das: Therefore, astronomy studies the object.
GOVINDA Das: And Jyotish Shastra studies the meaning.
GOVINDA Das: It is driven by philosophical thought. Next.
GOVINDA Das: Then comes the Devatas.
GOVINDA Das: Right? When people do Groha Shanti.
GOVINDA Das: There is a planet.
GOVINDA Das: According to the modern idea, then there is the Kraha, which is a powerful influence, and there are Devatas.
GOVINDA Das: Right, the Shani itself is not Devata.
GOVINDA Das: There is a person called a Shani who represents very, very deeply that particular planet.
GOVINDA Das: Hmm.
GOVINDA Das: Right.
GOVINDA Das: And because they use… The planet itself is not, oh, they're worshipping planet. We do not worship the planet.
GOVINDA Das: We worship… The representation of that.
GOVINDA Das: Certainly, You know, in the, like, if you study, I was studying one Western philosopher.
GOVINDA Das: spin was up.
GOVINDA Das: When he studied his own original background of Judeo-Christian, he was a Jewish person, what did he find?
GOVINDA Das: He found that God is always outside the creation.
GOVINDA Das: Hmm?
GOVINDA Das: But when you study, Bhagwat Gita, for that matter.
GOVINDA Das: What does Krishna say in the Bhagavad Gita? Umam Pashyati Saravatra Sar
GOVINDA Das: In the 10th chapter of the Bhagavad Gita, Krishna says, one who can see everything in me.
GOVINDA Das: And him in everything, please understand, 10th chapter is about.
GOVINDA Das: Seeing God in everything. Stavaradam Himalayam.
GOVINDA Das: Amongst the animals, among the devatas, the Uchesh Rabha.
GOVINDA Das: Among the kavis, I'm the ushanara Amongst the Pandavas I'm Arjun
GOVINDA Das: Among the flowing river, I am Jhannu, Ganga Nadi.
GOVINDA Das: Right? What does Krishna teach here in one sentence teaching?
GOVINDA Das: Abhay the tattva of seeing everything as a representation of God.
GOVINDA Das: And what does he do in the 11th chapter? He says, everything is in me.
GOVINDA Das: I'm in everything and everything in me, that is the 10th and 11th chapter.
GOVINDA Das: So, when we understand this… You know, then we choose the divinity there.
GOVINDA Das: Because it is not mundane. As I said.
GOVINDA Das: We are not looking for the planet, planet.
GOVINDA Das: We are looking for the substance within that Graha.
GOVINDA Das: So therefore, in the Vedic philosophy, a devata is an intelligent organizing principle within the cosmos.
GOVINDA Das: No, they, they are concentrated in regards to influencing that particular planet.
GOVINDA Das: When people under the guidance of proper Jyotish Shastra Gya.
GOVINDA Das: When he is connected to the particular Devata.
GOVINDA Das: According to that particular planet, or Griha.
GOVINDA Das: What does it do? The external…
GOVINDA Das: The subtle and the internal are harmonized. They do not creatable.
GOVINDA Das: No, they help us to grow.
GOVINDA Das: A fire governed by agni.
GOVINDA Das: Why you… Karan, can you move your picture? Because I'm not able to read some of it.
Dr. Karan Mittal: I don't know how to do that project, might just take a minute for me.
GOVINDA Das: Okay, TK. Wire is governed by Agni, wind by Vayu, sun by what?
GOVINDA Das: Whatever it.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Good year, and time and carving maturation by Shani.
GOVINDA Das: Okay, okay.
GOVINDA Das: So… So fire, right, fire is governed by agony.
GOVINDA Das: Just see the distinction. Thodasa, if you focus on that fire and agni, there's a different connotation altogether.
GOVINDA Das: And therefore, when the Western person, especially driven by Christian ideology, they'll go, oh, they're worshipping the fire. Oh, they're worshipping the wind. Oh, they're worshipping the, you know, the blazing sun.
GOVINDA Das: We don't worship fire, fire, we worship the agni.
GOVINDA Das: Right? We worship not the Hawa, we worship the Wahyu.
GOVINDA Das: And because… As we were discussing, That everything…
GOVINDA Das: One can see Krishna in everything. One can see God in everything. So even if it is fire, I will see Agni there.
GOVINDA Das: Even if it is wind, I will see why you there.
GOVINDA Das: Even there is sun, I will see Surya there.
GOVINDA Das: And I see karma being maturated, I see Shani there.
GOVINDA Das: He is giving, she is giving you darshan.
GOVINDA Das: Right, so therefore… Comparable to modern sciences laws of nature, but regarded as expressions of intelligence, not impersonal mechanism.
GOVINDA Das: So, what happens in Kraha…
GOVINDA Das: does accept the laws of nature. What are the modern scientists supposed to do? They are supposed to simply observe how it is functioning, not interpret.
GOVINDA Das: They do interpret for its utility.
GOVINDA Das: But Vijnana, the first step of Vijnana is to understand, to be aware of how it functions, why it functions.
GOVINDA Das: Right?
GOVINDA Das: So, therefore, Intelligence, so it is a, when we study the laws of nature of grahas.
GOVINDA Das: Then what does it do?
GOVINDA Das: It is… it is… Expression… But with intelligence.
GOVINDA Das: Hmm?
GOVINDA Das: That means when we express, that expression, if it has the flavor of buddhi.
GOVINDA Das: Then our understanding of the grihas become much deeper, much profound, and much beneficial.
GOVINDA Das: So, therefore, Devata is not a physical
GOVINDA Das: Devata is basically metaphysical category, not merely religious one.
GOVINDA Das: Religion is there. Religion means dharma is there.
GOVINDA Das: Right? But Devata… Achieves the higher position.
GOVINDA Das: You know, and he basically inherits.
GOVINDA Das: The energy of Kraha and planet.
GOVINDA Das: And then benefits the living entity. Therefore, tevatam is those who give light.
GOVINDA Das: Next.
GOVINDA Das: Can you explain this one, Karan, first one?
GOVINDA Das: Karan?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, so I was reading this book on Indian iconography, Hindu iconography, and it also mentioned that all the Grahas can be classified as per Adi Devik, Adi Bhavatik, and Adhyatmic principles.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Adi Bhotek is that planet that we actually look at.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Adi Daivik is that metaphysical entity that Shastra speak of, and Adjatmik is how it reciprocates inside our body in form of different organs and mentalities, etc. So.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, what we usually do is, we kind of, like, the modern day astrology or the modern astrologers kind of make it like a principle of causation. Because it is stated in horoscope like this, then it should happen like this. But the science of the Shastra of Jyotish was never a causation, it was not cause and effect.
Dr. Karan Mittal: it was the probability, what we have spoken, I think, in the first session also, it was a science of probabilities. That, okay, because the planets are placed like this, like this, the probability of this happening in one's life is very high.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So what we do is we associate a cause and effect relationship because this planet is like this, like this, like this, therefore this will happen in your life, but that's not how it works because yes, Adi Bhautikli, seeing the physical universe, you know, a picture of the horoscope, these planets will always, once you are born, these planets will always be.
Dr. Karan Mittal: in your horoscope in those positions only. But seeing it from that Ajhatmik and the Adi-Daivik lens, the ratio and the proportion, or…
Dr. Karan Mittal: when you do a japa or yajna or something of that sort, the adhatmic entity inside your body kind of changes, and that kind of changes the probability. So it's never about the cause and effect, it's about when you see something in the chart, there's a high probability, there's a high correlation.
Dr. Karan Mittal: that… that this can happen. And when you do a japa or a remedy, etc, also, there's a high correlation that the… the particular aspect or the particular effect of that planet changes. Yes.
GOVINDA Das: Yep.
GOVINDA Das: So it's very important to understand.
GOVINDA Das: You know, Jyotisha… It's… it's many times our language.
GOVINDA Das: We make the planets responsible.
GOVINDA Das: You know, planets are not responsible.
GOVINDA Das: They are simply an influence and putting that light about our own background, our own influence.
GOVINDA Das: Because the grahas means to influence.
GOVINDA Das: No, so similarly, the moon does not create your emotions, Saturn does not manufacture suffering.
GOVINDA Das: If your moon is debilitated or Saturn is combust.
GOVINDA Das: You know, so the indication is the indication.
GOVINDA Das: Is that, okay, moon does not create your emotions.
GOVINDA Das: Certainly. But if that moon is sitting in a particular place which is counterproductive to you, your emotions may come down.
GOVINDA Das: What are they doing? They're simply giving you a hint.
GOVINDA Das: They're not… they are not changing anything.
GOVINDA Das: Therefore, Satan also does not manufacture suffering, he is simply manifestation.
GOVINDA Das: You know, he's the representation of it.
GOVINDA Das: Not cause of it.
GOVINDA Das: Yes, what do the griha do in regards to karma? They simply signify the timing and pattern of karmic unfoldment.
GOVINDA Das: They make life easier, not in regards to changing the pattern.
GOVINDA Das: But to understanding the pattern.
GOVINDA Das: Just so the clock indicates time without producing it.
GOVINDA Das: Gras indicate karmic faces without independently causing them.
GOVINDA Das: The grahas do not cause any karma, they simply enhance, they simply
GOVINDA Das: You know, they are there to impact our consciousness.
GOVINDA Das: grahas are interpreters of karma, not creators of destiny. This is very important, so therefore.
GOVINDA Das: When somebody does Navagraha Shanti.
GOVINDA Das: That famous astrologer Bian Rao.
GOVINDA Das: He was asked, does Gra Shanti matter? Should we do it?
GOVINDA Das: He said… Of course, if there is a solution by that, if the expert astrologer is recommending that.
GOVINDA Das: One may do that now, Agra Shakti.
GOVINDA Das: But more important, More important was…
GOVINDA Das: If you're grounding your foundational principle very good.
GOVINDA Das: So then the grahas do not impact us so much.
GOVINDA Das: Right, if the foundational idea is very important, if it is understood properly, so what does it do?
GOVINDA Das: The Grahas, they are not creators of the karma, they are not creators of destiny.
GOVINDA Das: You know, but they are simply the interpreter of our karma.
GOVINDA Das: One indication they may give, therefore, the rishis have limitless permutation combination of astrological charts.
GOVINDA Das: Based upon that wisdom and based upon observing the creation, the Jyotish Shastrage and Jyotisha, they harmonize.
GOVINDA Das: And by harmonizing, what do they do?
GOVINDA Das: That gives us greater benefit. Therefore, grahas are not interpreter of karma, not creators of destiny. Grahas are interpreters of karma. So when you see one graha, I remember one, I've told this story many times.
GOVINDA Das: One person, he went to one Jyotish Shastra, by seeing his hand.
GOVINDA Das: The Jyotish Shastrage started jumping, oh my god, you know what? You know, he was telling the lady, he said, your son is going to have a lot of blood in his hand.
GOVINDA Das: Mother got shocked, oh my god, he might become a criminal.
GOVINDA Das: Hmm?
GOVINDA Das: So what she did, instead of going home, And crying for future criminal.
GOVINDA Das: She put him in a physical training. Then he joined the police department.
GOVINDA Das: Encountering 160 mafias, separatists, You know, what she did was… Rather than fighting it.
GOVINDA Das: Rather than encouraging it, she don't tell that properly.
GOVINDA Das: so that…
GOVINDA Das: It becomes beneficial to the living entities to perform the karma in such a way it is healthy, harmonious.
GOVINDA Das: Next.
GOVINDA Das: You want to say something?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Mmhm Yes.
GOVINDA Das: Yes.
GOVINDA Das: Yes. So, therefore, graha and ghar.
GOVINDA Das: Graham Pravesh.
GOVINDA Das: Ghar Pravesh.
GOVINDA Das: Graha.
GOVINDA Das: Right? They're all interconnected, and that is what Vastu is. Vastu is nothing but…
GOVINDA Das: Becoming part of that graha by alignment.
GOVINDA Das: When you become part of that Graha through alignment.
GOVINDA Das: Then you are simply deriving the positive principle of that planetary situation.
GOVINDA Das: Minimize the instability, maximize the stability is the purpose of.
GOVINDA Das: Planetary position.
GOVINDA Das: Yeah.
GOVINDA Das: My macrosome and microcosm mirror one another expression of same cosmic order Hritha.
GOVINDA Das: Same. There is no distinction between the two.
GOVINDA Das: Surya. What does Surya do?
GOVINDA Das: When somebody's house, especially Lagna or workplace.
GOVINDA Das: You know, then Surya represent consciousness and vitality, our ego, our ahankara, our astitva.
GOVINDA Das: And exactly opposite of that, Chandra.
GOVINDA Das: What does he do? He affects the Buddha. Buddha is basically information intelligent.
GOVINDA Das: Because, Chandra… It's Sanav. Buddha is Sanav Chandra.
GOVINDA Das: Guru is wisdom. Therefore, wisdom always moves very slowly.
GOVINDA Das: Moon moves very fast because moon is based upon feeling and feelings keep jumping back and forth.
GOVINDA Das: But Jupiter is almost like Sunny, moves slower.
GOVINDA Das: and if Jupiter is moving slow.
GOVINDA Das: Right? What does it indicate? Wisdom also comes in.
GOVINDA Das: in the later stages of our life. Wisdom does not come immediately, later stages.
GOVINDA Das: You know, shukra, value and relationship.
GOVINDA Das: Feeling, collecting the resources.
GOVINDA Das: And Shani representation, Shani represents limitations and maturation.
GOVINDA Das: Therefore, horoscope is symbolic map of consciousness, not merely chart of planets, profound statement.
GOVINDA Das: It's a symbolic map of consciousness.
GOVINDA Das: Yap karaega.
GOVINDA Das: And they are not… yes, they're mathematically precise.
GOVINDA Das: You know, this, this whole planetary position is mathematically precise, no doubt.
GOVINDA Das: And because it is mathematically precise, there is no prejudice.
GOVINDA Das: There is no cognitive bias in this.
GOVINDA Das: No.
GOVINDA Das: Prakriti, Griha's, because Griha is part of the Prakriti.
GOVINDA Das: Prakriti's brutally truthful, honest, they don't have sentiments.
GOVINDA Das: They don't care, oh my god, this has happened, so therefore I should not cause any more trouble. They are yama.
GOVINDA Das: And that Yamaha… What does he do? He simply becomes an observer
GOVINDA Das: And time to time, he might implement.
GOVINDA Das: the planetary influence.
GOVINDA Das: Therefore, horoscopy is a symbolic map of consciousness, not merely chart of planets. Remember this.
GOVINDA Das: Therefore, cosmos is read as a language of meaning.
GOVINDA Das: Therefore, because they see meaning in that language.
GOVINDA Das: Slowly, slowly, it becomes place of… Yoga.
GOVINDA Das: in connection to this planetary position. Next.
GOVINDA Das: Yes, the highest teaching of Jyotishya is not prediction but transcendence.
GOVINDA Das: Again, as I said, it is not that artificially one becomes transcendent.
GOVINDA Das: But that is the ultimate goal.
GOVINDA Das: But ultimate goal cannot be tracked to ordinary journey.
GOVINDA Das: Huh? And therefore, what does… what does the… Nar Singha Sheila do.
GOVINDA Das: What does the Jyotisha do?
GOVINDA Das: Highest teaching of Jyotis is not prediction but transcendence.
GOVINDA Das: I think I told is a physicist does a study quantum theory.
GOVINDA Das: They try to fix the past.
GOVINDA Das: Rather than trying to fix the future.
GOVINDA Das: When you fix the past, your future, your present, your super future, everything becomes benefited.
GOVINDA Das: Right?
GOVINDA Das: So, therefore, the Jyotish Shastra, it teaches profound perspective.
GOVINDA Das: Therefore, in the Bagutan Parlat Maharaj expl
GOVINDA Das: Prahlad was afflicted by Krishna Graha. That does not mean he denied them.
GOVINDA Das: Oh, I don't care for grass. That is not correct.
GOVINDA Das: I care for Grahas.
GOVINDA Das: I do what I need to do.
GOVINDA Das: At the same time, I try to experience transcendent.
GOVINDA Das: The Upanishads and Bhagavad Gita teach that Atman is beyond time, karma, and planetary influence.
GOVINDA Das: Right, the karmas do not affect
GOVINDA Das: Planetary influence doesn't affect. Do they affect?
GOVINDA Das: they affect minimal But not completely.
GOVINDA Das: And therefore, when not only identifying, when identifies with body and mind, grahas indicate the unfolding of karma, then 100% the impact will come as consciousness becomes established in the self.
GOVINDA Das: Through dharma, knowledge, and devotion, one is no longer psychologically bound by these influences.
GOVINDA Das: Physically, they might influence.
GOVINDA Das: But if you do proper rituals as recommended.
GOVINDA Das: So then what happens? Three things can happen.
GOVINDA Das: Your karma may vanish.
GOVINDA Das: Your karma is minimized.
GOVINDA Das: or you completely transcend your karma.
GOVINDA Das: You know, so before you transcend the grahas.
GOVINDA Das: Better to total the grahas in the service of God.
GOVINDA Das: Yeah, what we will do, the next part of the planet from the Bhagavatam, we will do after current
GOVINDA Das: Does the wash to part.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So continuing, so firstly, namaste, everyone. And, let's let's try to continue from from where we ended yesterday. So we saw the planets sorry. We saw the indirection. We saw the properties of the indirection briefly.
Dr. Karan Mittal: We also saw the five elements that these, directions kind of, all the, the four cardinal direction, subcardinal directions kind of.
Dr. Karan Mittal: re-present. We saw that part, and we also saw how to kind of map the center of the house and try to find the directions and the layout. And we continue from
Dr. Karan Mittal: there onwards today. Today, we'll try to kind of bring in the element of Devatas, Dashtadekpalas, we'll try to kind of correlate it with the planets, and then also see how the psychology of these directions that Rishis have conceptualized, and have kind of
Dr. Karan Mittal: said that… that which room should be where. So…
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, also, if you kind of also correlate it with the modern-day perspectives on neuroarchitecture, I think we'll see it on the last day, but just to kind of build the foundation.
Dr. Karan Mittal: If you see the foundational Vastu principles, there's a high correlation that you will kind of see in the principles that we find in neuroarchitecture. The neuroarchitecture is basically how a particular architecture kind of
Dr. Karan Mittal: Works on your mind, that's why the neuro part works on your well-being, works on your thought process, emotions, et cetera. So that's the neuroarchitecture part. And then the same thing, so it says that this, you know, like the Vastu says that the Brahmastan or the center of the house should be comparatively empty because whenever you look.
Dr. Karan Mittal: at… in the house, like, whenever you're sitting at one of the directions and kind of looking in the opposite direction, definitely you will be seeing the Brahmastan, because your eyes will pass through the diameter of the house. And when you have a…
Dr. Karan Mittal: When you have a broader perspective or an open perspective in front of you, and a strong support on the back.
Dr. Karan Mittal: That instills a sense of safety or elimination of fear because
Dr. Karan Mittal: We cannot see behind, so our mind was conditioned to kind of rest on something that's solid, behind you, like.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So kind of, you know that nothing is coming from behind. And when you have a broader perspective, you can kind of sense the dangers if they're coming from any of these directions. So the mind was conditioned in a way, or the evolution conditioned us in a way, to have something concrete or stronger at the back.
Dr. Karan Mittal: and a broader perspective in front of you. So that's how the Vastu also… of course, it's a normal, logical principle, but that's also how Rishis understood how space and how support affects our well-being. So they said that you, you know, sit in the southwest direction, which is the direction of earth element.
Dr. Karan Mittal: automatically instills grounding stability. And then you kind of look in the opposite directions. And when you look in the opposite directions, naturally the Brahmastan, or the center of the house, comes
Dr. Karan Mittal: somewhere there in your vision, and that instills a sense of safety because you're seeing a broader perspective. Similarly.
Dr. Karan Mittal: We discussed in the first session that more and more windows in the east, and in the north, and the northeast, and lesser windows in the south, southwest, because
Dr. Karan Mittal: The healthier part of the sunlight or the milder form of sunlight comes from the east and the west when the sun is setting, and the north kind of reflects the indirect sunlight, so kind of lights up the house but still doesn't put that intense heat into the house. So all these principles, which are rishis, of course.
Dr. Karan Mittal: You know, observed and brought it into the Vastu principles are also the principles of neuroarchitecture, and here again, I'm not trying to kind of prove that everything that's given in Shastra is found equivalent in neuroarchitecture, but the thought process of observation and coming to conclusions is still the same.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And, and, you know What we also saw in the second session, probably, is…
Dr. Karan Mittal: that your house is basically a representative of the Vastu Purusha. Now, there's a… there are stories in Puranas how this Vastu Purusha kind of, comes into the house, and then he gets the moon by Lord Dharma, and all that stuff. But basically, every house, everything that is bound by four walls.
Dr. Karan Mittal: The Vastu Purusha is placed with his front side facing the ground or the interior side facing the ground, so the face of the Vastu Purusha is facing the ground, and that's what we're seeing in this layout that's there on the screen right now. So you'll not see eyes or you'll not see the nose, et cetera, because the Vastu Purusha is facing the ground.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And the head of the Vastu Purusha is basically in the northeast.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So this is the northeast of the house and this is the southwest of the house. Now again, connecting it with yesterday's principle, northeast over here becomes the part of the head face neck region, this whole area. And now you can correlate why keeping it like that is important because the head of the Vasuparashtra is also in that direction apart.
Dr. Karan Mittal: From the planetary correlation that we saw last time, and also it is the direction of, as per the Vastu principles, the demigods.
Dr. Karan Mittal: the Devatashiva kind of resides here. So that's also another principle. That's why it stands for spirituality, meditation, and all that stuff.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And you will see that the legs, and legs kind of denote the stability or the movement, so the legs come in the southwest, and that's how the Vastu Purusha is. So.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Vasu also kind of tries to find out where, where exactly are the pillars and the walls in the house and the toilets in the house and they try to correlate in what part of the body does that particular wall or the pillar fall on and accordingly there are, of course, there are causes and effects or there are correlations that
Dr. Karan Mittal: than the Shastras Prasthaya. And that's why now you see the center of the house, it's the center, it's called the Brahmastana, because the presiding deity, or the lord of that area, is Lord Brahma. And also, if you see from the bodily coalition, it's the navel part.
Dr. Karan Mittal: of the vasculature, it's the stomach called the abdominal part of vasculature, and that's why it was told to be kept light, because imagine something heavy kept on the navel, and navel was considered to be the transmission of nutrients from the mother to the child, and vice versa. So, so, so the, the navel was
Dr. Karan Mittal: mentioned or kind of recommended to be kept light. So, every body part has some or the other
Dr. Karan Mittal: Correlations as per Rishi's, but we don't get into the depth, and also, just for your observation, you'll see that there are so many names that are given.
Dr. Karan Mittal: In the, in the square and with different colors. These are the different Devatas from different directions and different zones of the Vastu. So whenever you do a Vastu Shanti, these Devatas are kind of called upon. There's a Hawan that happens, and then, you know, you know, Yajna who used to please those Devatas. So that's the basic principle of Vastu Shanti.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, yes, so… so, in the slide, the last line that you see is basically the neuroarchitectural perspective, that when… when the… when the Brahmastan is empty and, you know, and the grids and the grids of the house are properly placed without too much of
Dr. Karan Mittal: Clogging or too much of clutter, the brain kind of senses a sense of safety, a sense of clarity, because more the things are there on my table or in front of me.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Even though I'm not, like, now I'm paying attention to this thing while I'm talking, but even though I'm paying attention to this thing, my brain is taking cues, visual cues from all the things that are there around me.
Dr. Karan Mittal: The more the number of things, the more the brain needs to process it subconsciously, and it kind of induces stress. That's why study table, etc, or your working desk, etc, was mentioned to be clutter-free.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So these are the five, many few slides would be repetition just to kind of brush up what we did last time. So these are the four directions, subcontinent directions with their four elemental correspondences. And the center, of course, is space or ether or the Brahmasthan, which is more the empty element of the space element.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So usually.
Dr. Karan Mittal: what happens is, like Ravji also mentioned, we kind of try to panic, we get panicky when we understand that, okay, the Northeast has the kitchen or the toilet. Usually, all these elements, the toilet.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Or on the… the kitchen, etc, need to be there in the house, and it's just about
Dr. Karan Mittal: trying to balance the five elements in correspondence to the particular room that is there in that particular direction. So, so, and the Northeast has toilet, so definitely the water element is getting affected. So, the pro- the solution over here is not to kind of
Dr. Karan Mittal: break the toilet and make a new somewhere else. The solution over here is that the water element of the house needs to be enhanced in different ways, which we'll try to cover up today.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So yes, so, so how do we look at the map of the house? We look at from the perspective of that BT, Graha element water governance. We also look at, look at.
Dr. Karan Mittal: at… from the… from, look at it from the principle of what particular room is there in that direction, who is sitting in that particular room, or who is utilizing that particular room, and also, how… how is that particular room structured in itself? So, three things.
Dr. Karan Mittal: One is the Shastri principle, the Graha, the planet, the Devata, the element, et cetera.
Dr. Karan Mittal: The room, per se, in a sense, kitchen being located in the southeast, northeast, northwest, so which room is located where?
Dr. Karan Mittal: how the internal structure of that room is also kind of placed. That is also equally important. So…
Dr. Karan Mittal: So we'll come to it. So this we saw last time, so I'm not kind of repeating it.
Dr. Karan Mittal: how does Northeast actually work? So, Northeast basically is the brain or the head part of the Vastu Purusha. It stands for Guru as a planet, or Jupiter as a planet, which is for clarity. And it is also for spirituality, because the residing Devata is basically,
Dr. Karan Mittal: Shiva. So, now see how I'm correlating. I'm taking the elemental properties, the properties of water, I'm taking the planet's properties, and I'm also taking the Devata's properties, and that's how you kind of understand what this direction stands for. So.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Clearing the northeast automatically brings in the positivity from the Jupiter planet, the wisdom, the clarity of mind. It kind of gives you peace of the mind because the spiritual aspect of the house opens up. Also, the water element.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Because 70% of our body is made up of water, which Ayushi has recognized, so the water element of the house starts improving and automatically it starts reciprocating in your body as well. So now what's the psychology of the room of naughties? So basic.
Dr. Karan Mittal: psychology, it's a… it's a direction of spirituality, peace of mind, it's a direction of kind of… not inertia, but it's a direction of clarity of thoughts. So, who should be idly
Dr. Karan Mittal: staying in this direction. First thing that we all know of through social media, etc, is the temple of the house, because that's where peace, spirituality, clarity, etc. needs to come in. What are the other things? What other things could be there? So.
Dr. Karan Mittal: How the rooms of people who geriatric people or old age people who need to kind of, you know, start becoming more, more peaceful and need to have, need to kind of go deeper into spirituality. People who are very spiritually oriented can easily and safely start sleeping in the Northeast if there is no other option available.
Dr. Karan Mittal: studying people children who want to study so the study room can go in North is because it brings in Clarity of mind so you have to now start correlating what is the property of the direction and who could be best suited to inhabit that particular Direction so these this is what you'll find in shastras also it's not like you need to kind of rote learn everything know the direction and you know what what will work there
Dr. Karan Mittal: Of course, now, going from the anti-element theory, of course, kitchen and water element, we don't bring in kitchen, because that's the anti-element. So, kitchen in that direction, we need to do a remedy, we need to strengthen the water element of the house. So, that… that needs to be understood
Dr. Karan Mittal: How do we read a plan? Before… I think you all might be now having the layouts of your house. If not, please utilize this week to kind of fetch or get, you know, fetch the layouts, find the Bhumasan, find the directions, so that
Dr. Karan Mittal: this whole course is fruitful to you. How do we look at the
Dr. Karan Mittal: layout at our level. First, we saw yesterday, we see there are NT elements. If northeast has fire element, if southeast has water element, we try to find if there is an NT element.
Dr. Karan Mittal: we see if there's a cut or extension. We'll come to what this cut or extension means. And we… the third point that we see is if there is contamination, which direction or which element is getting contaminated by… by a toilet or something of…
Dr. Karan Mittal: something like a toilet, a bath from a toilet. So, which direction is getting contaminated? That we see, from the Vasudev principles. These three are the things that we actually see at the basic level Vasudev. So, so what is a cut or an extension? So now, suppose
Dr. Karan Mittal: this is the layout, this is the… the layout of my house. Now, it's logical that now, if I want to create a quad, I'll just choose the laser.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So if I want to create a layout of this house, and I make this quadrilateral that we discussed last time, and we find the Dhammasthan, et cetera, what I find is the northwest, east, et cetera, everything is included in the house. But the northeast part of the house and a predominant part of the north area is excluded from the house.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, this is a cut. The northeast is cut from the house proper. So, this I will count as northeast, and when the northeast is cut, automatically the water element is outside the house. It is not coming in my own ship.
Dr. Karan Mittal: The element of Jupiter planet has… is eliminated. The element of deity of Shiva, that is, spirituality meditation, is eliminated. So, this will start showing effects of water deficit, what I shared yesterday's slides, and it's uploaded on the app also. So.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So it will show symptoms of water deficient.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Probably, if I go…
Dr. Karan Mittal: In this particular plot, now what I see is the nearest or the biggest quadrilateral that I can make is this, okay.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, what I see over here is this particular area.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Of course, it's a part of my ownership, it's a part of the house, but it is kind of extended, in a sense.
Dr. Karan Mittal: This is the biggest quadrilateral, then this is kind of falling outside the quadrilateral, outside that square, and this I will count as extension of the house, and this will show symptoms of northeast extension, or that is excess of water in there, so over, over emotions or.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Whatever, whatever I mentioned yesterday. So, we see from the cut or the extension perspective. Now, some people ask, how do we decide whether it's a cut or extension? Now, now, supposedly, if I take this plan, so how do I decide if northeast is cut.
Dr. Karan Mittal: On, on.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Or even…
Dr. Karan Mittal: this part, the kitchen, the toilet, etc, is extended, because I could very well make this also a quadrilateral, and consider this as an extension. Then we go as per the symptoms, okay? If we see that
Dr. Karan Mittal: there is a problem with the mental clarity, psychological issues, then we'll consider it a Northeast cut. But if I see if there is an excess of aggression, excess of…
Dr. Karan Mittal: anger issues, fire element issues in the house, etc, then I will take this as a southeast extension. Of course, there's a mathematical rule to it, 10% of the total area of our house, but symptoms work the best, in my experience. So that's how you kind of, associate the cut extension. So three things. Cut and extension.
Dr. Karan Mittal: anti-element and contamination form of toilets.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, how do… how do we kind of balance? Now, we're coming to the remedies part. We'll kind of cumulatively understand the remedies in the next session also, but I'm just starting to mention that how there are different remedies for GV cost. You don't need to always
Dr. Karan Mittal: kind of break things and make, you know, reconstruct things. There are Jivik elements, there are different principles, as we understood, Adi-Bharatik, Adi-Laymik, Adi-Ahtmik. There are various Adi-Ahtmik remedies, Adi-Bharatik remedies to balance that particular direction. So, Northeast, we know, is the water element direction. So, definitely
Dr. Karan Mittal: the symbolism of water element in that particular direction kind of energizes or balances the water element. So.
Dr. Karan Mittal: a pitcher of flowing water, or a fountain, these things are mentioned, like, you know, see social media. Why are these mentioned? Because it symbolizes water and increases the effect of water in that particular house. Clear pot is, again, a crystal.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Clear quotes is a representative of the water element listed.
Dr. Karan Mittal: There's something called as color activation, which we'll see eventually in the fifth session. Every element or every direction has colors that the Rishis have given, and then
Dr. Karan Mittal: Kind of increasing that tone or increasing the proportion of that particular color or decreasing it vice versa, it depends, will balance that particular element.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Trishul, Nawai Trishul. I'm explaining the logic because it becomes easier than in the other seven directions. So, Trishul is basically the
Dr. Karan Mittal: The weapon of Lord Shiv, or even Omar stands as a representative. So, so.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So it kind of increases the strength of that particular delta in the northeast direction.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Of course, what we discussed last time, clearing the Northeast also brings in that auspiciousness into the house. Donation of milk and milk products, symbolizing the Dhana part of the Jyotish and Vastu. Shivopasana, so some amount of Shivopasana also
Dr. Karan Mittal: Increases that component of that delta in your body automatically because the water element is contaminated or reduced in the house, increasing the ratio of the ratio in your body of that component by starts negating the effect of the component that is the spatial component of.
Dr. Karan Mittal: the Vastu. Emotional intelligence and Vastu, again, are, again, an adhypnic exercise, like working on your emotions, psychology, psychotherapy, mindfulness, all those things. And silver water. Silver is the element of, of…
Dr. Karan Mittal: Northeast direction. So, you know, like, we drink copper water, but, copper water in, in form of waterless, you know, putting a one or two set of coins into the water and drinking. It is also mentioned to increase
Dr. Karan Mittal: That anthropic component of not distension, so this is the logic in the remedies. Remedies are not something that, that, that, like, like, you know, you, if you understand the logic of that direction, you'll also understand the logic of the remedies, and you can start doing your remedies, like the anthropic component of your remedies, by your own self.
Dr. Karan Mittal: No.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So this is the anti-element thing. I've… I've mentioned it yesterday, so I'm not repeating it. Of course, I'll share the slide for you to refer in future. So what is the anti-element of which particular direction is mentioned in the slide, and how it affects,
Dr. Karan Mittal: affects availability.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Coming to the southeast, we have discussed southeast's fire elements, so we saw the basic,
Dr. Karan Mittal: like, what, what does the Southeast stand for? Now, the planet for Southeast is basically Shukra, or the Venus.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And the Devata is Agni Devata, that's why the fire element. So now you need to start understanding fire element and shukr. So fire element, basically, whatever we mentioned last time.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Passion, activity, aggression, the, of course, it's also the yang side or the male side, so it also starts for the male, stands for the males of the house.
Dr. Karan Mittal: up.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Chukra, there's Venus, there's the planet of creativity, desire, so it also stands for all those things. It also stands for the cash flow inside the house. Agni is basically your digestive system, so it also stands for the digestion. So if the southeast is cut, then automatically these things will start lacking in the house. If southeast is extended, these things will start.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Showing the symptoms of excess, excess of anger, excess of digestive issues.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yeah.
Dr. Karan Mittal: All those things put together. So now again, coming to the psychology of Southeast, Because it's fire element.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Or it's because it's probably under the domain of Venus or Agni. What could be the ideal thing in the Southeast? Naturally, it's fire element, so no water element can be there because it's Agni or the anti element. So naturally, no toilets can be there.
Dr. Karan Mittal: the most predominant area of fire element in the house is the kitchen. So, naturally, the kitchen goes in the southeast as per Vasco, and also.
Dr. Karan Mittal: the MCV, the main control board can go there, the generator can go there. Anything that stands for fire element, what you feel has heat, or radiates heat, can automatically go into the southeast zone. Now, what is the color of southeast, for fire?
Dr. Karan Mittal: So anything that has too much of red or copper use also goes into the southeast direction.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So… so… so that's the southeast as a property. Who… who can sleep? If you don't have… if you have a bedroom, probably in the southeast, and you don't understand who can sleep there. Of course, we'll not put an old-age person over there, because they'll become more aggressive, then we… there will be more misunderstandings.
Dr. Karan Mittal: you will not put the owner of the house, because the direction of southeast… southwest is for the owners of the house. So naturally, the kids of the house can safely sleep in the southeast shelter, there is no other option.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, that's how you try to understand. It goes from the decreasing order, like, the owner goes in the southwest, and then, accordingly, we decide the other, inhabitants of the house.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Now, how… suppose your southeast is cut, or there's a contamination in the southeast in form of toilet, how would you purify, or how would you, increase the fire element of the house? Of course, lighting at the,
Dr. Karan Mittal: lighting a lamp, or placing a lamp over there is one way of doing it. Doing a small home on Agnihotra in the southeast is recommended in Shastras also, that the ideal place for fire worship for Agnihotra is the southeast direction.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Because it's fire element, it cannot be dark, it cannot be shady, it cannot be humid, it cannot be gloomy. So definitely clearing the area and having the light lit there.
Dr. Karan Mittal: to depict that fire element definitely improved the Southeast. Agni Upasana is basically a homom that is Agni Hotaras.
Dr. Karan Mittal: how do we work on the adhatmic component, or the internal body component is, by increasing the fire element in the body, and that happens through many panels, like Nastrika Kabbal Bhate Panel increases the fire.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So people who have a southeast cut, and their aggression, or their passion, or their drive to do things is lacking, doing bhastrika automatically stimulates the manipur chakra and the fire element of the horse. So that's the Dhyatme component.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Of course, we try to put warm colors over there, basically colors from the warmer shades, like red, copper, whatever depicts the fire element.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And copper water. Like, we have silver water for,
Dr. Karan Mittal: Vishanya, that is northeast. Similarly, copper water for southeast.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Now, this verse is basically from Ramayan.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And when Lord Dawn is selecting the cave, to reside in Kishkinda.
Dr. Karan Mittal: He… this is the… there are 7-8 verses, but I've selected the most, appropriate verse, where he speaks about how the cave should be as per Vastu principles. He says that the southwest of this cave
Dr. Karan Mittal: It's a huge wall, but it's, like, completely covered.
Dr. Karan Mittal: and the northeast is you know there's a slope that comes from the southwest to the northeast and the northeast is preferred so this is the best way for us to reside in Lakshman that's what he's mentioning in this verse there's three four other words or maybe seven more verses that come that speak about different was principles so here he's mentioning that the southwest needs to be heavy
Dr. Karan Mittal: covered with a… covered with a wall, and the Northeast needs to be, like, open, and kind of broader in perspective, and… and this also involves
Dr. Karan Mittal: A very basic understanding of the geographic or the climate of the country, most of the wind or the rains that come to India are the southwest rains, so the rains or the wind are basically moving from the southwest direction towards the north, so having a covered southwest kind of prevents those.
Dr. Karan Mittal: diamond rains coming into the house. So, so, so that's what is the geographical understanding, or the climatic understanding of the principle, but also.
Dr. Karan Mittal: that, that the principles of Vastu were mentioned in Brahman itself. So, Yeah.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, so southwest is basically… there's a mistake over here. South… I've written southeast, understanding the psychology of the rules and the people for southeast. It's southwest. So southwest, basically, we know as earth element. It's basically the element of heaviness. So the heaviest area of the house, if you have to store weights, you have to store…
Dr. Karan Mittal: Heavy things, you have to store dumbbells, you have to store metal, you have to store anything that is heavy that needs to come in the southeast
Dr. Karan Mittal: So it kind of creates that heaviness of the earth element that the house needs. And of course, because it's earth element, the remedies are also
Dr. Karan Mittal: Oh, sorry, I need to cover the psychology. So now, because it's…
Dr. Karan Mittal: we discussed it yesterday, because it is… the heaviness is the component over here. People who need to have authority, who need to have stability, who need to… need to ground themselves are the best people to stay, or sleep, or sit in this direction, so that's the owner of the house.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, whether it's the workplace or the house, it's that the owner of the workplace or the house should be situated in the southwest, because it gives them that grounding and stability that the owner needs.
Dr. Karan Mittal: What are the remedies? Of course, earth element, so early colors, and not keep on repeating the logic. Of course, if…
Dr. Karan Mittal: You know, your southwest has a big balcony, or it has a big window, and it's lacking weight when you increase weight in the southwest.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay? It will always do good, rather than any harm. So we increase the weight in Southwest by keeping dumbbells, metal, metallic objects, all those things, you know, storage of the house can go there.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Oh.
Dr. Karan Mittal: what… what would symbolize weight is also the imagery of a mountain. So… so people… people place as remedies the… go… like, any… any mountain image there. Also, the southwest is also connected to the, the planet Rahu.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And the… the Devata, or it comes in that… it's… it's a rakshas over here, it's Nehrupti, is the presiding deity of the southwest, and they are… this direction is connected to the ancestors of the house. So the southwest is a problem.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And then doing Bitri Taipana or Shada on a regular basis, etc. If stability of the…
Dr. Karan Mittal: stability of people in the house, mentally, physically, financially is the problem. This component also could be taken into account from astrological and vascular perspective combined together.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, you can place trees, you can place, heavy plants over there, with the care that you don't increase too much of water.
Dr. Karan Mittal: water the plants as much as needed. The water shouldn't be dripping, 24 by 7, so…
Dr. Karan Mittal: Don't increase the water element over there. So you can keep things that are plant related over there. Yeah.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Of course, there are… of course, it also relates to the earth elements, so working on the body by punch karma or doing grounding meditations also helps in increasing that earth component from the abdominal perspective, and thereby kind of
Dr. Karan Mittal: Thereby kind of purifying that earth element and in reducing the effects of a negative southwest.
Dr. Karan Mittal: on on your body.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Pure architectural perspective, like I said, I think in one of the sessions also, that if earth element is lacking in your body, choose things that, like.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Whenever you choose your sitting position, your bed, et cetera, choose things that signify that stability and support. So chairs with probably having a proper backrest up till your head, kind of whenever you take the backrest, you know that there's a support. So that's now telling me trying to be bare feet, at least in the house, increases your connection with the world when you are.
Dr. Karan Mittal: sleeping on the bed, then having a proper headrest, or a proper pillow that doesn't shake, or doesn't… like, it's stable enough to give you a sound sleep. All these things also start increasing the earth element,
Dr. Karan Mittal: At that meeting, you know what.
Dr. Karan Mittal: The Northwest Zone.
Dr. Karan Mittal: It's the Vayuvya or the Vayu. We might not be able to complete all the eight. We'll try to complete at least two more before we go to questions. So Vayu, of course, the planet over here is Chandra, that is moon.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And the Devata is YU Devata. The Devatas that I'm mentioning for the Eight Directions are basically your Rashti Niqbalas, the guardian deities of the Eight Directions. So, even when we do Yamdha, when we do… we are doing, Sapna, or any kind of Puja, these Eight Devatas are invoked
Dr. Karan Mittal: In fact, they are requested to kind of protect that particular karma that you're doing, that particular web game you're doing, because they are the guardian deities of these eight directions.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And that's why in one of the principles of Basu, the weapons of these devatas… I'll share a photo on the group also. The weapons of these devatas are very important because,
Dr. Karan Mittal: like, like, you can add, like, we added the shul in the northeast direction. In the eastern direction, we had a bajrawa. Like, there are different, like, in Wayuu, we have a flag that is the weapon of the Wayuu Day. So these, these,
Dr. Karan Mittal: weapon signify protection, coming from them. So, Northwest is basically Moon, and also, Vayu Delta. So, now, get into the wind element, Moon, and, and, Vayu Delta. So, it's all about movement.
Dr. Karan Mittal: of the mind, movement of the body, movement of businesses, movement of goods. It's about flexibility. It's about communication. It's about social relationships, because if you don't go out.
Dr. Karan Mittal: then how will you have social relationships so it's going out not not as just doesn't mean physically but also mentally emotionally you should be approachable you should be able to approach people it is also about mental well-being because moon basically and it also signifies the daughters of the house so Southeast was
Dr. Karan Mittal: Suns, the male progenies, northwesters, the female progenies of the house, so, so.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So that's Northwest for us. Anyone who moves a lot, anyone who needs movement in their life, they are to be told that, like, they have to be stationed in the Northwest. So it would be the kids of the house if they're, you know, going out. People who are able to travel in the tourism industry can also be in the Northwest of the house.
Dr. Karan Mittal: travel a lot because of their work, or their study, or any of the other components of life, can be stationed in the Northwest. So Northwest is basically movement, so whoever requires movement.
Dr. Karan Mittal: can go there. If a person is becoming very lethargic, very inertia-prone, so they can also be stationed in Northville, because it will give them that necessary, boost from the Vastu principle to move.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yeah, so that's Northwest. Kitchen, for kitchen,
Dr. Karan Mittal: southeast is the west direction, but northwest is the secondary direction of Kichanastha Shastras. So,
Dr. Karan Mittal: If, if not the Southeast, Northwest also equally, is okay to have a kitchen there.
Dr. Karan Mittal: newlywed couples can go in the Northwest to preserve the dynamism in their life. So, that's about the Northwest corner. Coming to a factory or a workplace perspective, definitely the finished goods of the factory or the
Dr. Karan Mittal: or the company are going to be stored in the Northwest, because it gives them the moment, so they are kind of
Dr. Karan Mittal: more and more, there's more probability to be sold, like, faster if the finished goods are sold in the Northeast.
Dr. Karan Mittal: What are the balancing…
Dr. Karan Mittal: remedies,
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yeah, so basically, because it's a YU element, the balancing remedies, of course, is good ventilation in that particular part of the house.
Dr. Karan Mittal: anything that signifies moving air, that is wind, so wind chimes or bells, also are placed. Now, this is a modern neo-Vastu, remedy, but still it works, because… because it signifies movement of the air in that.
Dr. Karan Mittal: particular place. We add aromatic, because it's YU element, we add aromatic things only, so aromatic white flowers or a diffuser, et cetera, could be added in the northwest.
Dr. Karan Mittal: We we allow moonlight to come into this area because, of course, moonlight, is like moon is the the presiding the planet for this, area.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Of course, from an anthropic perspective, pranayama movement therapy does work. If the lotus of the house is spiked or contaminated, etc, doing regular prana basis increases that YU component in your body and probably nullifies the vascular impact on you.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Moon worship, Chandra Namaskar. So, so…
Dr. Karan Mittal: That is… that is one, too.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Brass is the element of Northwest, so…
Dr. Karan Mittal: either you place some artifacts or some, some, decorative things, aesthetic things related to brass in that particular direction. Of course, not very heavy, but something that, correlates, something that is made up of brass. And again, donation of wine products comes from, the planet.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So that's… that's about the Northwest.
Dr. Karan Mittal: remedies.
Dr. Karan Mittal: last time we saw these axes, so now there are 3 axes, what we mentioned. One is the solar axis, the sun rises in the east, sets in the west, okay? So that's the solar axis from east to west, and that's why
Dr. Karan Mittal: We mentioned in the first session also, the thickest wall needs to come in this direction because this is the most aggressive time of the sun rays.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And there's a magnetic axis that starts in the north and kind of ends in the south, so that's the magnetic axis. And there's a pranic axis that starts in the northeast and ends at the southeast. So these are the three axes, and different things
Dr. Karan Mittal: are kind of oriented as per these access differently. So so.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Because this is high cosmic energy, and now, if you also see, this is the, intersection of the positive north part and the positive east part. So this becomes ultra-positive. So, so having things that
Dr. Karan Mittal: Need high, high spiritual, like, things like meditation, spirituality definitely starts in Warrior. Things that need too much of inertia are tamas bone. It's an intersection of west and the south, the southwest, so the west sleeping direction goes in the southwest, so, so.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Even the accesses or the recommendations to see to work are also aligned to these access. Okay, now, now, when you're working or when you are kind of, study, it's usually said that you face the east or the north because you're facing the east or the north, you're inviting the energy of the north, that is the magnetic energy or the solar energy.
Dr. Karan Mittal: into your body, and that enhances your prospects to have a better grasping. So these axes also play an equal and opposite equal role, apart from the eight directions. Tuji, would you like to take the Bhagavatam part?
GOVINDA Das: Yes, Karan?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Would you like to take the Bhagavata Or, or should I continue?
GOVINDA Das: So, you continue this, because
GOVINDA Das: Or you… first you'll take some questions, because there's a lot of information.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, we do. Sure, sure.
GOVINDA Das: Yep.
Dr. Karan Mittal: If you take questions, because now we have completed the four subcardinal directions, next we have the four major cardinal directions, east, west, north, south.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So before we jump into that, if there are questions, if I'm going too fast, if you want me to repeat anything, please, please, please ask.
NAman Kashyap: So, Prabhuji, can we take the questions which, Gov.
GOVINDA Das: Yeah.
GOVINDA Das: Anything, anything.
NAman Kashyap: Yes, yes, okay, thank you, Budhi. So, Budhi, we were discussing about, so my basic question is,
NAman Kashyap: Even if I understand, that, you know, what might be upcoming, or, like, we are taking the hints. Suppose, for example, if there's a particular dasha, so, we may not do something, or we may… we may do something, or we may not do something. My question for you is how to trust that.
NAman Kashyap: I mean, in the sense that if some, some changes coming up, the astrologer might say, or through this own study, I.
NAman Kashyap: tend to know that, okay, from after 6 months, Dasha is going to change. But that trust, okay, I… so suppose… the practical question is, I want to change a job.
NAman Kashyap: And I was I'm like after this study also and before some esthology also that this year is not suitable. It's not good. You wait for January. The Dasha, the Antar Dasha is changing to Rahu. That would be a better time.
NAman Kashyap: So my question to you is that how do I trust that? And I mean, so how do I build that trust? I mean, so that is the question.
GOVINDA Das: So, if there is a contradiction between your present.
GOVINDA Das: That is Prathiksha Pramana, there are 3 Pramanas, always we should remember.
GOVINDA Das: One has to always operate on the principle of integrating three pramanas.
GOVINDA Das: The Pratyaksha Pramad, Anuman Pramad, and Shabda P
GOVINDA Das: If the Jyotish Shastra is giving huge contradictory claim about your present and the future, it is always better to focus on the Prataksha Pramana.
GOVINDA Das: Because the protection is visible, And profitable.
GOVINDA Das: Like, if you say, okay, your job is very good.
GOVINDA Das: And you're only changing your job to make more Progress.
GOVINDA Das: Right? Or then astrologers say, no, no, something is going to go wrong. Right? But the pattern is not shown.
GOVINDA Das: Pattern has not shown, you may, you might become extra careful, not concerned, not panicky, and continue doing what you're doing.
GOVINDA Das: So, it is important that Jyotish Shastra gives mostly what happens…
GOVINDA Das: We don't understand the language what they're speaking.
GOVINDA Das: Second, when they are speaking, it is like when they get into the chart of a person, it is like an oceanic information.
GOVINDA Das: Depending upon how much they are involved, how much they are interested, how much…
GOVINDA Das: You know, time they have. So they'll focus on one or two things.
GOVINDA Das: Probably, invariably, what happens… Either one or two principal mess, so therefore the responsibility of
GOVINDA Das: Interpreting the interpretation of the Jyotish Shastra Gya is the responsibility of the person who has approached him.
GOVINDA Das: Therefore, the basic understanding.
GOVINDA Das: Of Jyotish Shastra is very important, the language.
GOVINDA Das: You know, if that understanding is not there, then we simply accept their order rather than discuss with them.
GOVINDA Das: Back and forth discussion will give much better clarity.
GOVINDA Das: If your chart is correct, your date of birth is correct, your timing is correct.
GOVINDA Das: And if there is a correct calculation.
GOVINDA Das: There are greater probability in regards to the planetary influence.
GOVINDA Das: How exactly that translate into your reality from a physical perspective, whether you will go to America, whether you go to some other country.
GOVINDA Das: Specifically, it says there is a favorable
GOVINDA Das: Because this planet is sitting on the 12th house.
GOVINDA Das: And if you're 10th house's master is sitting in the 12th house, it indicates there is a foreign. Now, foreign not necessarily means some other country. Foreign also means far away from your home.
GOVINDA Das: how they interpret. Nowadays, they interpret foreign means outside country only.
GOVINDA Das: Garsedur, far away. So, therefore, it is very important that applying logic always helps in regards to understanding, interpreting, reinterpreting what the Jyotish Shastrage has told. Otherwise, they want to get fast, okay?
GOVINDA Das: No.
GOVINDA Das: That is an important principle and not nobody should take an abrupt decision like Karan was explaining yesterday also you know when you after studying.
GOVINDA Das: was to… And you see that, oh, there are many faults in your house.
GOVINDA Das: Abruptly doing something will not benefit because it will cause disturbance in your family also. What are you doing?
GOVINDA Das: Therefore, again, Shanay, Shanay, slowly, slowly, slowly, you know, you change.
GOVINDA Das: That is the process of.
GOVINDA Das: Jyotish Shastra again was to nothing abrupt.
GOVINDA Das: It's a science. It's a vidya.
GOVINDA Das: That is important.
NAman Kashyap: So, Puruji, wish… so, I mean, like, by this course, or subsequently, I should be… try to equip myself with that understanding, like, yes, we have till now got to know about the Lagna, Rashi, and Nakshatra, but, I mean, that we will be doing.
GOVINDA Das: Yeah, so that's what you will, you will, you will understand, you understand the language.
NAman Kashyap: Yes, for you.
GOVINDA Das: Now, that is a common language, but that common language has not created favorable mindset in the people. It has only created a problem. As I said, Sade Sat is not an occult number. It is just measurement, to end half, to end half, to end half.
GOVINDA Das: You know, so immediately you're, okay, no, this is not, this is not as I used to hear from my childhood. Sadhisatthi is the movement of the shani towards moon, and depending upon where it is sitting, if somebody's sadhisatthi is happening in the 12th house, 11th house.
GOVINDA Das: Lagna, you know, they will have a different impact. Somebody is having on the 9th house, 10th house, 11th house, it will have a different impact. Somebody is happening on the 4th and 3rd and 5th house, it will have a different impact, even though happening in the same time. So that permutation combination, once you understand it, has a mathematical precision.
GOVINDA Das: You know, it will create the impact.
GOVINDA Das: In regards to mental impact.
GOVINDA Das: Satya Sathy And through that mental impact, it might create certain patterns.
GOVINDA Das: So therefore, in the…
GOVINDA Das: In one of the Puranas, I remember one Jyotish Shastrage said, the predictability of any astrologer is only 50%.
GOVINDA Das: Just because they predict few things, You know.
GOVINDA Das: One of the famous astrologer, P. Vinar Singh Rai, you must have heard
GOVINDA Das: You know, he does a lot of prediction, but he also says not all prediction will come true, that indication.
GOVINDA Das: No, he had predicted Trump will not win, but he won.
GOVINDA Das: No? So, it is not the dust lodger…
GOVINDA Das: You know, then you cease to become a human.
GOVINDA Das: And if you're a devata, you're not supposed to stay here interacting with human beings.
GOVINDA Das: You know, Jyotish Shastra is also human only, so therefore they give an indication. They do not give assertive, certain reality.
GOVINDA Das: So the responsibility of using our logic, Depends upon us only.
GOVINDA Das: Integration.
GOVINDA Das: Yeah, Prashant Kumarji.
Prasath Kumar R: Hare Krishna would you pron
Prasath Kumar R: Raviji, the one statement in a slide saying that, you know, the chart is the map of the consciousness, not the group of planets.
GOVINDA Das: Oh, okay.
Prasath Kumar R: very profound statement. Any reference from a book or a.
GOVINDA Das: Correct.
GOVINDA Das: Hello?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Final terms and conditions.
GOVINDA Das: Yeah.
Prasath Kumar R: Well, it might.
GOVINDA Das: That is the… that is a very profound statement, you know, it makes.
Prasath Kumar R: Yeah.
GOVINDA Das: Yeah, it makes the logic see.
GOVINDA Das: One thing we have to understand.
GOVINDA Das: When we read any scripture or Vedic knowledge.
GOVINDA Das: If it is new way of…
GOVINDA Das: Understanding the same Siddhanta, the words may not be there exactly there in the book.
Prasath Kumar R: Correct, correct.
GOVINDA Das: But but it it makes a lot of sense. So when it makes a lot of sense.
GOVINDA Das: You know, the language, the word, somebody must have used it differently, but the principle you'll find, but the detail you will not find exactly, but it's a perfect understanding. Therefore, you're asking that question because it makes sense.
Prasath Kumar R: The principle, I'm fully convinced with the principle, but my doubt is like, say, for example, a Mahesh Lagna person, so very Kshatriya nature is a Mahesh Lagna. So ruling planet is Guja. So this is vigorous, but in this Lagna.
Prasath Kumar R: When Merkur is present, Buddha is present.
GOVINDA Das: Okay.
Prasath Kumar R: He will be like very intellect and very fast also, right?
Prasath Kumar R: But his Lakhna Devati go and sits in the, what you call the cancer, Karkarashi.
GOVINDA Das: Oh.
Prasath Kumar R: What kind of consciousness he will have? That's my doubt.
GOVINDA Das: Yeah, so that is… therefore, it is the flow, like, if you go to… I was in Rishikesh the
GOVINDA Das: you know, the flow of water in Ganga, depending upon the changing of the season, the color also changes. So the 12 planetary positions, they're flow of energy, they're not blocks.
GOVINDA Das: You know, they're not bricks They're not… they're not, Ghana Vastu.
GOVINDA Das: You know, their Dravia, their flow, their.
Prasath Kumar R: Got it.
GOVINDA Das: Planet.
Prasath Kumar R: Change, dynamic and changes.
GOVINDA Das: Yes, therefore Gra is not a planet. Huge difference in understanding when we use your own mother tongue, especially the Bharatiya Bhashas.
Prasath Kumar R: Mmhm.
GOVINDA Das: So the meaning, the word itself gives you the meaning, the flair.
GOVINDA Das: Right? Planet means it likes a box. When you crawl means a flow.
GOVINDA Das: No? So therefore, it… and that… and again, our teacher would say, as you study.
GOVINDA Das: The common sense when it is applied and you study more and more charts, then you realize, oh, this permutation and combination gives rise to this kind of mindset.
GOVINDA Das: You know, what is, how did Rishi Parashar.
GOVINDA Das: wrote his book.
GOVINDA Das: You know, the data collection was based upon observation. They must have studied the cosmos.
GOVINDA Das: Studied the people because the rishis, rishis are people who are not introvert. Rishis are introvert internally, at the same time connected to the society.
Prasath Kumar R: Yeah. You know, it'.
GOVINDA Das: original data science. So therefore, they have that capacity to explain. And that is what the beauty of Jyotisha Shastra Gya become much more clear in his hypothetical understanding.
GOVINDA Das: And confirms through Shastra and confirms through Prataksha Pramana.
Prasath Kumar R: This course gave a few eye opener. Prabhuji, like this statement, you know, the horoscope is symbolic representation of your consciousness, not the group of planets. And also the kras are not causing your karma or, you know, any this thing. They're like a bank cashier. It is in your account. They will give out. If it is not there, you cannot get got it. Beautiful. Thank you. Thank you so much.
GOVINDA Das: Any other question.
GOVINDA Das: Karan, you want to add No.
NAman Kashyap: Prabhuji, I, I thought Abhijit will ask, but, so, current, current, sir, I wanted to check, as you mentioned, southwest is the second best direction for kitchen. So, my question is not.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Or just for south, southwest?
NAman Kashyap: Oh, sorry, it's Northwest, Northwest, yeah. So, actually, my kitchen is in Northwest only, as of now, but the… the question is, the 2BHK,
NAman Kashyap: The kitchen itself is of 3 zones. I mean, 2 to 3 zones.
NAman Kashyap: So then, then how to, I mean, like, so, I mean, some, some, some friend who is into Vastu, he told me that you put the gas here and not there. So what does that kitchen means? I mean, so, I mean, how to go in that? Because you mentioned that there are 16 directions as such.
NAman Kashyap: So, I… when I was purchasing my home, so I tried to do that, and I have my section in 16 zones. So, my kitchen itself is in, 3…
NAman Kashyap: 3 zones, so… what is the suggestion there, sir?
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, next session, we'll cover that internal architecture, internal layout of every room. So we'll try to cover that. If it's still unanswered, then I'll probably answer it. But then, what we do is, in that room itself, we try to align the gas stove in the south, like, in that room, southeast direction.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So it's like the… we call it as the son master. In a sense, we have a grandfather, father, and the son master. In that particular room, we take it to the southeast, the southeast corner of that particular room, because that's the file element of that particular kitchen of foods.
GOVINDA Das: So basically, you subdivide the house into four directions.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes. And subdivide the kitchen again into 8 directions, as per, like, what we made. So we try to align with that.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yep.
GOVINDA Das: Again, the beauty of, beauty of Dharma Shastras, it to be relevant to the modern context.
GOVINDA Das: You know, otherwise… That is what Smriti is. Smriti is also very dynamic.
GOVINDA Das: You know, it's very interesting what solution he told. It's… it's not feeling, hopefully, oh my god, I need to change my home now. You know, then people invest their money, lose their money. So, always there are alternatives. If you cannot do this, do this. If you cannot do this, do this. That is how
GOVINDA Das: Even Krishna in the Bhagavad Gita, 12.8, 12.9, 12.10, 12.11, he says.
GOVINDA Das: Same principles applied in every aspect of our life, including Ayurveda, Vastu, Shastra, everything.
NAman Kashyap: Preeti, last small question going to you. I mean, do you mention it is Griha Pravesh or Griha Pravesh Pravesh? It's Griha Pravesh or Griha. Griha means home. So that was a bit confus
NAman Kashyap: We call it Griha Pravesh.
GOVINDA Das: Sanskrit scholar, current is the Sanskrit scholar, what is the.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Griha is the house.
NAman Kashyap: Like we have issue.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Thanks.
NAman Kashyap: Okay, okay, okay, that's it.
GOVINDA Das: Yes, Prashant.
Prasath Kumar R: Prabhuji, quick one. In Southwest, if there is no bathroom, what is the remedy, Prabhuji, in South.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yeah, southwest bathroom, usually, we try to increase the earth element,
Dr. Karan Mittal: like, outside the bathroom, and we try to keep the bathroom as dry as possible. Like, we make it, like, you know, using those mops, etc, to clear… to make it to not let the earth element get, nullified by the water. So that's the remedy. We'll come to, the remedy in the next session, like, how…
Prasath Kumar R: Okay, thank you.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Oops.
GOVINDA Das: Abhijit.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yeah, you're not.
GOVINDA Das: Can't hear you.
Dr. Karan Mittal: You can type if needed, Avijiti, and we can address it later.
GOVINDA Das: Yeah, we can read, yeah.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, should we stop here, or not?
GOVINDA Das: You have a question on that?
GOVINDA Das: You can type, you type, you can type.
GOVINDA Das: We can wait.
GOVINDA Das: Meanwhile, there's one more question.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So Sonaliji's question, what is the remedy if the kitchen is in the west? We'll come to the remedies per se. Let's wait for the next session. Of course, we cannot go into every specific remedy for every particular defect, but how to balance that west zone, we'll come to that part in the next session.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And I'll also upload the matter on the content of today on the app, so you can refer whatever we have.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Nothing to know.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Probably, the question is…
Dr. Karan Mittal: I have been told of Kalsatva Yoga. I did Remedy Brown Bath. Should I do it again?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Aviditz, Aviditz discussed.
GOVINDA Das: Yes, currently answer.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yeah, so…
GOVINDA Das: Okay.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So… There are two thoughts to it.
Dr. Karan Mittal: First thought is, basically, once a remedy is done, like, these yoga remedies, you don't need to do it again.
Dr. Karan Mittal: But experientially speaking, and I've interacted with a few very, very traditional astrology scholars of
Dr. Karan Mittal: of India. They say that the Karamkanda that happens today is not the Karamkanda that is exactly prescribed in Shastra, so the efficacy of those things are not as what Rishi's wanted. And in Taluga also, the remedy becomes four times of
Dr. Karan Mittal: what was meant for the Satyagraha. So, they say that these yoga shantis should be done periodically, like Vastu Shanti needs to be done every few years, Kal Satpa Shanti, etc, also every 12 years or something. They prescribe doing it. And also, it also depends on the symptoms. Like, I was seeing a horoscope a few days ago.
Dr. Karan Mittal: If the symptoms are very evident, the symptoms have restarted, etc, then it's better to do it
Dr. Karan Mittal: That's my take to it, yes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: What I've understood from the tour.
Prasath Kumar R: That was a quick one.
Prasath Kumar R: The present Gochara, if you see, all the planets lies in between Rahu and Ketu, all its seven planets. So now who are the children born? They're born with Kalashar Padosh.
Prasath Kumar R: Yeah, because the moon also within the Rahu, all the planets lie in, if you see sun, moon, everybody, everybody, all the seven planets between Rahu and Ketu. So the children born during this period have similar, either if it is yoga.
Prasath Kumar R: They all become flourishing. If there is dosh, all of them are suffering.
Prasath Kumar R: This is the question I have. What will be the… But still, based on the Lagna, the impact will change. But based on the Moon, Rashi aspect.
Prasath Kumar R: Everybody born in Kalasharpathos.
GOVINDA Das: It's current.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes. So now.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, yes, so that's what I think in the first session I mentioned also. Lagna horoscope is the most… is the broadest perspective of looking at a horoscope, but on a daily, hourly.
Dr. Karan Mittal: or basis, weekly basis, these planets change degrees. So, probably all of them will have Kal Sattva in their Nagna Kundi. As we go into micro Kundis, it changes. So, the effect of the Kal Sattva
Dr. Karan Mittal: Will still be there, but the intensity of these effects will keep on changing.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay, so, so, and also Moon doesn't stay in a rashi more than two, like, more than two and a half days. So, Moon is a fast-moving planet. So, even in just a week or so, sometimes the Kala Sapphanalifas. So, so, it depends on all these things put together. It's not just the Nagnapuri.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Or you, yeah.
Prasath Kumar R: Thank you very much. Thank you.
GOVINDA Das: Stop here. Thank you.
GOVINDA Das: We'll see you on Friday.
NAman Kashyap: So, Pooji, will… sorry, will we get some more handouts? I mean, this whole week, exercises and things?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, yes, yes, definitely. I'll also send all those remedies, et cetera, for you to reflect on the anti elements in a bit. Maybe in a day or two.
NAman Kashyap: Yes, yes. And just last, Goenjuji, like, kindly guide to fix the past while a partner. I mean, philosophically, I try to… it's… it's… I understand that instead of, you know, trying to worry about the future and…
GOVINDA Das: Yes, yes, you can remind me.
NAman Kashyap: Yes, sir Thank you for that.
NAman Kashyap: Thank you.
Dr. Karan Mittal: There was a direction.
NAman Kashyap: Alex.